Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Scrapbooks and Clippings, 1709-1974 MS 3158
New-York Historical Society
- Various pictorial works, 1870s? (Offsite-box 63)
  One volume of small, color illustrations of children, animals (sometimes in clothing), flowers, women in various styles of clothing, expressions of affection, caricatures, and the like.
- Mrs. Albert T. Weston scrapbook, 1870s-1880s (Offsite-box 27)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings, which appear to be from St. Louis, concerning various medical and health matters. Inserted in the volume is a copy of a letter from the Health Commissioner of St. Louis, dated 1879, providing a statement of the births, stillbirths, and deaths in 1878 in the African-American population of the city. Source: Gift of Mrs. Albert T. Weston, July 2, 1931.
- Literary and other clippings, 1870s-1880s (Offsite-box 54)
  1 volume of clippings on various literary, cultural, and historical topics. Most seem to concern British figures, though some clippings relate to the funeral of U.S. President James Garfield. The volume opens with some handwritten poems.
- Thomas J. Burton scrapbooks, 1870s-1918 (Offsite-box 30)
  Thomas Burton was a member of the Society of Amateur Photographers who collected engravings or other pictorial works of historical New York and made lantern slides of those illustrations. These 3 volumes relate to Burton's work: one volume is a "catalogue of cuts & illustrations" of churches and ministers; a second volume is mostly notes on the chronology and ministers of various Protestant sects, with various clippings throughout; and the third volume holds clippings with pictures of contemporary (circa 1870-90s) buildings. An envelope with the scrapbooks holds photostats of views, circa 1918.
- Louisa Morris Stewart Kent (Mrs. James Kent) scrapbooks (Box 1 of 4), 1870-1911 (Offsite-box 14)
  10 volumes of newspaper clippings.
- Louisa Morris Stewart Kent (Mrs. James Kent) scrapbooks (Box 2 of 4), 1870-1911 (Offsite-box 15)
- Louisa Morris Stewart Kent (Mrs. James Kent) scrapbooks (Box 3 of 4), 1870-1911 (Offsite-box 16)
- Louisa Morris Stewart Kent (Mrs. James Kent) scrapbooks (Box 4 of 4), 1870-1911 (Offsite-box 17)
- Annie Skeel Burnap floral scrapbook, 1871 May-August (Offsite-box 63)
  A small scrapbook of dried plants obtained from various places in Europe, specifically from locales in England, Switzerland, and Scotland. Each plant is captioned, identifying the plant, specific location from which it was gathered, and date. Source: Gift of Mrs. Roswell Skeel, Jr., May 6, 1948; the donor's husband was Burnap's cousin.
- George Watters scrapbook, 1871 October-December (Offsite-box 22)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings centered principally on the New York elections of 1871, with themes related to Tammany Hall, Boss Tweed, corruption, and electoral fraud. There are also some clips about the Chicago fire that also occurred in October 1871. Source: Gift of the estate of George S.M. Watters, January 23, 1888. (See also Watters at 1881)
- Trade cards and other advertisements, 1874-1877 (Offsite-box 63)
  One volume of trade cards, handbills, flyers, and other publicity items for various New York City businesses.
- C.J.W. Summers scrapbook, 1874-1904 (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings, likely from Virginia newspapers, which is the state inscribed by Summers in the album. The bulk date is 1874 and includes mostly poetry. There are some articles on financial matters, and some ephemera about the First National Bank of Alexandria. A couple of items dating from 1895 and 1904 appear to have been added at some point. The album was originally part of N-YHS's Folk Arts Collection of November 17, 1937.
- Julia Stevens scrapbook, 1875-1876 (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume of Revolutionary War Centennial clippings. Source: Gift of Warwick Potter, October 9, 1956. According to a note by Potter in the volume, the scrapbook was compiled by Julia Stevens, sister of the historian and N-YHS member John Austin Stevens. Potter was a great-nephew of Julia Stevens.
- Programs re: Frederick Specht performances, 1875-1889 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 folder of programs for concerts at which the tenor Frederick Specht sang. Included in the material are 3 documents related to a banquet given U.S. President Grover Cleveland by the Merchants Association of Cleveland (menu booklet, program, and seating chart). Source: Gift of Specht's sister, Amelia Specht, May 4, 1950.
- Marguerite Adelaide Wolfe (Mrs. Grenville Kane) scrapbook, 1877-1878 (Offsite-box 6)
  1 volume compiled by Miss Maggie Wolfe, as she is referred to in the album documents. The scrapbook contains memorabilia of Wolfe's social events, including lunches, dances, cotillions, and drives. Memorabilia includes newspaper clippings, programs, invitations, pressed flowers, ribbons, bells, and other ephemera. Wolfe captions the pages to indicate what event they were from. Generally, they appear to relate to society in Narragansett, Rhode Island, and often involve a type of event or dance called a "German." Toward the rear of the volume are pressed plants from a bouquet from Grenville Kane, whom she would marry, as indicated by her use of her married name on the upper flyleaf beneath her maiden name. See also the "Of Interest to the Kanes" scrapbook below at 1906.
- Lispenard Stewart scrapbooks (Box 1 of 4), 1878-1913 (Offsite-box 37)
  7 volumes of newspaper clippings compiled by Lispenard Stewart (1855-1927) and centered on himself. The articles concern both his political career (he briefly held office as a state senator in New York, and was active in electoral politics and the Republican Party); his social activities, including dinners he hosted or attended, summers at Newport, etc.; social gossip, especially about his various rumored marriage engagements (he was a lifelong bachelor); his involvement with New York's prison commission; and other matters. Many of the articles also relate to his family, including his brother William Rhinelander Stewart (1852–1929). Source: Gift of William Rhinelander Stewart, November 17, 1928.
- Lispenard Stewart scrapbooks (Box 2 of 4), 1878-1913 (Offsite-box 38)
- Lispenard Stewart scrapbooks (Box 3 of 4), 1878-1913 (Offsite-box 39)
- Lispenard Stewart scrapbooks (Box 4 of 4), 1878-1913 (Offsite-box 40)
- George E. Horn scrapbooks (Box 1 of 2), 1878-1964 (Offsite-box 32)
  2 volumes of newspaper clippings regarding the New York City elevated railroad/subway system; one volume ranges from 1878-1892, and the other from 1931-1939. There is also a small box that holds Transport Workers union lapel pins from the 1930s-40s; some timetables; several Suburban Rapid Transit Company contracts with New Jersey Railway Construction Company (1880s-90s); a typescript of various notes of Chief Engineer Robert I. Sloan of Manhattan Railroad (1870s-80s); and a 1928 booklet of rules and regulations of the Interborough Transit Company. A few items extend to 1964. Source: Gift of George E. Horn, October 15, 1958, apparently with some small additions later.
- George E. Horn scrapbooks (Box 2 of 2), 1878-1964 (Offsite-box 36)
- Edith Stiles scrapbook, 1880s (Offsite-box 26)
  1 volume of clippings, mostly of literary items, poetry, and anecdotes; illustrations; cards; and some correspondence. Stiles lived in St. Louis and the documents seem to be from that city.
- John E. Stillwell scrapbooks (Box 1 of 2), 1880s-1890s (Offsite-box 27)
  2 volumes, primarily of newspaper clippings. This first volume holds clippings of poems and stories. Source: Gift of the estate of John E. Stillwell, April 29, 1931.
- John E. Stillwell scrapbooks (Box 2 of 2), 1880s-1901 (Offsite-box 58)
  This volume relates to Ann O'Delia Solomon, also known as Editha L. Diss Debar. There are some letters and a purchase agreement concerning Stillwell's purchase of oil paintings from Diss Debar about 1883. The bulk of the album holds newspaper clippings related to Diss Debar, a spiritualist, and her legal difficulties.
- George Watters scrapbooks. President Garfield death and Guiteau trial, 1881 (Offsite-box 63)
  2 volumes of clippings compiled by George S.M. Watters concerning the funeral of Garfield and his assassin's trial. The volumes are marked as numbers 3 and 4 so the set is not complete, but it is not known if the volumes are still extant or have yet to found at N-YHS. (Also see an earlier scrapbook by Watters above at 1871.)
- William Alfred Robbins scrapbooks (Box 1 of 2), 1881-1893, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box 44)
  2 volumes compiled by Robbins related primarily to certain aspects of his academic and professional life. The volume from the 1880s-90s includes documents from his studies at Brooklyn Collegiate & Polytechnic Institute and at Yale College (Class of 1886), tickets, calling cards, appointments as notary public, railroad timetables, programs, organization memberships, and documents from his travels in Europe and on the West Coast of the U.S. The volume from 1918-19 documents Robbins's position as an overseas secretary for the YMCA War Work during and in the aftermath of World War I. Robbins was based in France and many of the documents are consequently in French. Documents include correspondence, photographs, postcards (including several with drawings depicting the consequences of war's trauma on children), passport, maps, clippings, etc. Many documents are on stationery of the Les Foyer du Soldat, Union Franco-Americaine. Source: Gift of William A. Robbins, July 3, 1947.
- William Alfred Robbins scrapbooks (Box 2 of 2), 1881-1893, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box 45)
- Jacob S. Manheimer scrapbook, 1881-1931 (Offsite-box 4)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings.
- "Articles on 'Old New York'", 1882-1898 (Offsite-box 6)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings of descriptions of New York of the early-mid 19th century.
- Florence R. Carey (Mrs. Florence Carey Hand) scrapbook, 1883-1899 (Offsite-box 26)
  1 volume of cards, calendars, correspondence, advertisements, and trade cards. Source: Gift of Florence Carey Hand, June 25, 1931.
- Howard Sloat scrapbook, 1883-1910 (Offsite-box 2)
  1 volume containing theater programs, correspondence, and newspaper clippings. Source: Gift of Howard Sloat, April 22, 1948.
- Sarah Althea Sharon vs. William Sharon scrapbook, 1884-1885 (Offsite-box 25)
  1 volume of clippings documenting some of the courtroom drama, which took place over several years, in the San Francisco-based matter of adultery, divorce, and alimony concerning former U.S. senator William Sharon and Sarah Althea Hill, or Sarah Althea Sharon as she claimed to be Senator Sharon's wife, the matter in dispute. George Washington Tyler was Hill/Sharon's lead attorney and also figures prominently in the clippings in connection with his provocative courtroom actions. The compiler of the scrapbook has not been determined.
- Betsey (Bessie) van Nostrand Smith scrapbook, circa 1884-1919 (Offsite-box 25)
  1 volume of theater and musical programs and clippings. Source: Gift, April 2, 1954.
- Sydney H. Carney, Jr. Book, 1887 (Offsite-box 8)
  Copy of handwritten manuscript: "Infectious diseases: being a report of the lectures at the College of Physicians and Surgeons, N.Y., by Prof. Francis Delafield, recorded and arranged by Dr. C.H. May for the special and exclusive use of his Quiz Class." Inscribed by Charles H. May.
- Jonathan Ethelbert Brush scrapbook, 1887-1889 (Offsite-box 58)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings compiled by J.E. Brush (1818-1889) of New York City. Though a layman, Brush was involved with several religious (Protestant Christian) and charitable efforts. He was a member of St. Paul's Evangelical Church. Most of the clippings in this album reflect his religious interests and apparently are drawn principally from the "Herald of Religious Liberty." Many of the articles were written by Brush. The articles range from brief announcements of events, such as religious conferences/gatherings, to longer articles about spiritual matters. There are many articles on religious personalities, their appearances/public remarks, obituaries, etc. Brush was on the Board of Control and treasurer of the Franklinton (North Carolina) Mission, also known as the Franklinton Colored School, so several clippings pertain to that. There is a cabinet card photograph of Brush. Source: Inscribed in the album is a statement of its provenance: It was a gift to N-YHS from Thomas Ollive Mabbott in September 1922, who purchased it at a bookstall.
- Sydney H. Carney, Jr. scrapbooks (Box 1 of 5). Volume 1, 1894-1915, 1880s-1918 (Offsite-box 8)
  5 volumes plus one book (listed separately above at 1887) compiled by Dr. Sydney H. Carney, Jr., MD. Gift of Dr. Carney, April 13, 1946. This first volume primarily holds documents related to his membership in the Society of Colonial Wars in the State of New York. Documents include correspondence, yearbooks, addresses/speeches, meeting announcements, toasts, event programs, treasurer's statements, etc. A small number of documents are loose at the front of the album and these relate to both the content of this scrapbook and the others.
- Sydney H. Carney, Jr. scrapbooks (Box 2 of 5). Volume 2, 1890-1918, 1880s-1918 (Offsite-box 9)
  This volume holds documents related to Carney's membership in the Society of the Sons of the Revolution in the State of New York. Similar to volume 1, documents include meeting announcements, programs, circulars, correspondence, annual reports, etc. Connections to World War I emerge in the volume. Some loose documents related to the scrapbooks as a whole are at the front.
- Sydney H. Carney, Jr. scrapbooks (Box 3 of 5). Volume 3, 1893-1910s, 1880s-1918 (Offsite-box 10)
  Carney was a member of New-York Historical Society. He was Recording Secretary and member of the Executive Committee from 1900-1904. For a time he was on the Building Committee during the initial construction of the Central Park West building in the early 1900s. This third scrapbook primarily includes documents related to Carney's membership and positions of responsbility at N-YHS. Documents in that regard include correspondence from other historical societies, meeting and other announcements, printed lectures, photograph of Librarian William Kelby, acknowledgements of Carney's gifts to N-YHS, and print matter concerning the developing new building. One unique document here is architect York & Sawyer's original design for the trowel used for the groundbreaking. The album also includes documents from Carney's memberships and interests in other religious, cultural, and other organizations. These especially include the Cathedral Choir School of St. John the Divine and programs etc. from several other churches.
- Sydney H. Carney, Jr. scrapbooks (Box 4 of 5). Volume 4, circa 1890s-1907, 1880s-1918 (Offsite-box 11)
  Carney's fourth volume holds advertising ephemera. Documents include pamphlets, brochures, booklets, circulars, order forms, handbills, trade cards, letters, etc. Consistent with Carney's profession, the bulk of the advertising relates to medicines, food, treatments, sanitoriums, health/nutrition guides, therapies, and the like. But there is a wide range of other products found here as well, including clothing, banks/financial, cultural events, travel/transportation, etc. Toward the rear of the album are some political ephemera and clippings.
- Sydney H. Carney, Jr. scrapbooks (Box 5 of 5). Volume 5, 1880s-1906, 1880s-1918 (Offsite-box 12)
  Carney's fifth scrapbook includes calling cards, event invitations, some dance cards, programs, etc. from across a wide range of types of institutions, including religious, social clubs, academic, military, cultural, literary, and leisure (e.g. automobile club).
- "A reminder of a lovely summer at Schooley's Mountain [New Jersey]", 1890 September 4 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 small volume with 6 pictorial works, inscribed "from Bo Peep and Red Riding Hood." Source: Acquired July 6, 1937, but donor not recorded in N-YHS accession ledger.
- George Ehler Stonebridge scrapbooks, 1890s-1930s (Offsite-box 28)
  4 volumes of newspaper clippings (and some full newspapers), programs, bulletins, invitations, postcards, pamphlets, etc., compiled by photographer and lecturer George E. Stonebridge (died 1941). N-YHS holds a large collection of his photographs and some family papers. One of the volumes primarily centers on announcements and other ephemera related to Stonebridge's public lectures for the New York City Department of Education and others, 1907-26. The other three volumes include clippings about Stonebridge, poems and articles that he wrote and were published in the press (e.g., the North Side News), published images of his photography, and ephemera related to his membership in the Bronx Society of Arts and Sciences and other organizations. Overall the documents relate largely to Tremont and other areas of the Bronx. (The volumes were likely donated in 1942 with the photographs, but separated.)
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks (Box 1 of 4). Boxing, 1890s-1930s (Offsite-box 47)
  4 volumes of newspaper clippings concerning the sport of boxing and boxers, dating mostly from 1892 to 1902, with some clippings out to the 1930s. The first two volumes were compiled by John J. (Jack) Donoghue, the third by Charles Stephan, and the third unidentified. Comprised heavily of articles and images from the National Police Gazette, the scrapbooks trace the history of boxing at the turn of the 20th century, which includes boxers of color such as Joe Walcott, Frank Craig, George Godfrey, Peter Jackson, and others. One album includes some cigarette cards of boxers. Two of the volumes have autographs on the opening pages, including that of John L. Sullivan (1900). Source: Gift of J.B. Stack, November 4, 1953. (See also Stack's volumes on general New York history noted above circa 1829.)
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks (Box 2 of 4). Boxing, 1890s-1930s (Offsite-box 48)
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks (Box 3 of 4). Boxing, 1890s-1930s (Offsite-box 45)
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks (Box 4 of 4). Boxing, 1890s-1930s (Offsite-box 49)
  This volume has three autographs inside the front cover: John L. Sullivan, James D. Carroll, and John F. Mumford.
- Mrs. Edward Rutledge scrapbooks (Box 1 of 3), 1890s-1947 (Offsite-box 42)
  4 volumes of clippings, which are heavily pictorial with few text-based items. Content is primarily of the British Royal Family, American politicians including the Franklin D. Roosevelt family, and other celebrities, social elites, historical figures, and artists. Material related to women comprise a substantial portion of the clips. Many of the pictorial works are of artworks. Source: Gift of Mrs. Edward Rutledge, September 14, 1954.
- Mrs. Edward Rutledge scrapbooks (Box 2 of 3), 1890s-1947 (Offsite-box 43)
- Mrs. Edward Rutledge scrapbooks (Box 3 of 3), 1890s-1947 (Offsite-box 46)
- David Dows obituaries scrapbook, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings regarding David Dow's failing health and death. Most clippings are obituaries from various newspapers.
- Blanche Louise Smith scrapbook (Box 1 of 2), circa 1891-1909 (Offsite-box 18)
  1 palimpsest volume. The underlying oversize book is a product catalogue from Desblocker-Block Tailoring Company of Buffalo, NY, for Fall & Winter, 1898-99. Many of the original pages are fully visible, some with the remains of fabric swatches. Other pages were covered by Smith with theatre and other cultural event programs and other ephemera, especially related to Canisteo (NY) High School, from which she seems to have graduated. Especially notable is that several doilies are laid into the scrapbook, with notations on them as to the dinner, picnic, or other event they were used at.
- Blanche Louise Smith scrapbook (Box 2 of 2), circa 1891-1909 (Offsite-box 54)
  A folder of documents, found on the shelves apart from the scrapbook volume, these seem to be loose documents that likely fell from the scrapbook and were separated at some point. Includes small items of correspondence, calling cards, commencement invitations and programs, Valentines, tickets, ribbons/pins for the Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor (Y.P.S.C.E.) conventions in Steuben County for 1898 and 1906, and other such mementoes. Some of the items appear to have been stained by colors running from slight water damage. There is a small notebook with some entries that appear to concern travel to prayer meetings in Boston and in Washington, D.C.
- Religious-themed scrapbook, circa 1892 (Offsite-box 58)
  1 slender album of clippings with a religious theme. Most are undated, but those that are dated are 1892, with some perhaps somewhat earlier. Generally, the articles seem to center on the views of various ministers (e.g. Lyman Abbott), religious views on prohibition, social notes on religious figures, and perspectives on other religions of the past.
- Wilmot T. Cox scrapbook, circa 1893 (Offsite-box 2)
  1 volume containing ephemera, prints of portraits and other artwork, and illustrations. Source: Gift of Wilmot T. Cox, August 21, 1942.
- Herbert T. Wade scrapbook, 1893-1930 (Offsite-box 1)
  1 volume containing certificates, programs, and ribbons from various banquets and events.
- "A History of Deerfield [Massachusetts], with Genealogies" by George Sheldon, circa 1895 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 volume of clippings of Sheldon's "A History of Deerfield [Massachusetts], with Genealogies." The compiler of the clippings in this volume is unknown.
- Emanuel Hertz scrapbook, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 5)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings of political cartoons and other illustrations. Source: Gift of Emanuel Hertz, April 24, 1930.
- Newspaper cuttings, 1897-1901 (Offsite-box 26)
  2 small volumes of newspaper clippings, with the compiler's brief comments or captioning on several of the clips. The first volume holds clippings from 1901 concerning the stock market and corporations generally, with comments suggesting the emphasis here is on the manipulative and speculative aspects of the market. The second volume holds clips from 1897-98 and an introductory contextual comment concerning bicycles and bicycling, with special emphasis on the League of American Wheelmen. Source: Gift, September 19, 1923.
- Scrapbook of calling cards, 1897-1922, undated (Offsite-box 67)
  One volume from an unidentified compiler of calling cards, in alphabetical order, mostly from New York City. Only a very few cards are dated.
- John H. Judge scrapbook, 1898-1903 (Offsite-box 66)
  One volume with meeting notices; announcements of meetings, lectures, dinners, etc.; invitations; and some clippings related to various New York City clubs, especially the Colonial Club of New York, for which Judge was Secretary during this period. The scrapbook holds the 1899 annual financial report of the New York City Democratic Club. There are a few abstracts of meeting minutes of the West End Association, which included reference to opposition to running 4 trolley tracks on Amsterdam Avenue.
- Dexter Cabot naval military clippings scrapbooks (Box 1 of 3), 1898-1912 (Offsite-box 55)
  7 volumes of newspaper articles and images principally concerning the U.S. Navy, including battleships, uniforms, weaponry, officers and personnel, etc. The earliest entries seem to date from 1898 with extensive references to the U.S.S. Maine. One volume seems to include somewhat more articles on European ships. 6 of the volumes were either explicitly labeled as compiled by Dexter M. Cabot, or can be clearly linked to him. One volume is less clear as to the compiler but seems to also be that of Cabot. Source: 6 of the volumes indicate they were acquired on November 7, 1919, though there is no entry for them in the N-YHS accession ledger.
- Dexter Cabot naval military clippings scrapbooks (Box 2 of 3), 1898-1912 (Offsite-box 56)
- Dexter Cabot naval military clippings scrapbooks (Box 3 of 3), 1898-1912 (Offsite-box 57)